<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <id>https://pyemma.github.io/</id><title>Coding Monkey</title><subtitle>I am a coding monkey, and I am proud of it. I have done lots of work in machine learning area, especially recommendation system and AutoML. This blog summarize my journey to become an expert monkey in distributed system and LLM.</subtitle> <updated>2025-02-10T21:40:14-08:00</updated> <author> <name>Coding Monkey</name> <uri>https://pyemma.github.io/</uri> </author><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://pyemma.github.io/feed.xml"/><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" href="https://pyemma.github.io/"/> <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator> <rights> © 2025 Coding Monkey </rights> <icon>/assets/img/favicons/favicon.ico</icon> <logo>/assets/img/favicons/favicon-96x96.png</logo> <entry><title>How to Design Slack</title><link href="https://pyemma.github.io/How-to-design-slack/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Design Slack" /><published>2025-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</published> <updated>2025-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated> <id>https://pyemma.github.io/How-to-design-slack/</id> <content src="https://pyemma.github.io/How-to-design-slack/" /> <author> <name>pyemma</name> </author> <category term="Distributed System" /> <summary>In this post, I would like to discuss how to build slack, a very popular realtime messaging application, especially for group messaging (a.k.a channel) in cooperation messaging scenario. Functional Requirements Channel messaging (group messaging) and thread message (reply to a message in a channel or DM) Direct messaging (1 to 1 messaging) Support sending message to both online and off...</summary> </entry> <entry><title>Recsys 2024 Paper Summary</title><link href="https://pyemma.github.io/Recsys-2024-Paper-Summary/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recsys 2024 Paper Summary" /><published>2025-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</published> <updated>2025-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated> <id>https://pyemma.github.io/Recsys-2024-Paper-Summary/</id> <content src="https://pyemma.github.io/Recsys-2024-Paper-Summary/" /> <author> <name>pyemma</name> </author> <category term="Machine Learning" /> <summary>In this post, I would provide a quick summarization to some papers from Recsys 2024 which I think is pretty interesting and worth a read. The list of paper is selected based on my personal research &amp;amp;amp; study interest and is highly objective. I highly encourage you to review the accepted papers as well and I’m happy to discuss if there is some great paper I missed out. There are around 20 pap...</summary> </entry> <entry><title>Trend of Sparse Features in Recommendation System</title><link href="https://pyemma.github.io/Machine-Learning-System-Design-Sparse-Features/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trend of Sparse Features in Recommendation System" /><published>2024-11-03T00:00:00-07:00</published> <updated>2024-11-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated> <id>https://pyemma.github.io/Machine-Learning-System-Design-Sparse-Features/</id> <content src="https://pyemma.github.io/Machine-Learning-System-Design-Sparse-Features/" /> <author> <name>pyemma</name> </author> <category term="Machine Learning" /> <summary>In my pervious post, I have briefly mentioned about sparse features and how they could be used in recommendation system. In this post, let’s have a deeper look into sparse features, as well as reviewing some new ideas about how sparse features are being used in modern recommendation system, especially in the realm of LLM world. What is sparse features Sparse features are usually composed as s...</summary> </entry> <entry><title>How to Design Online Chess Game</title><link href="https://pyemma.github.io/How-to-design-online-chess-game/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Design Online Chess Game" /><published>2024-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</published> <updated>2025-02-03T20:08:32-08:00</updated> <id>https://pyemma.github.io/How-to-design-online-chess-game/</id> <content src="https://pyemma.github.io/How-to-design-online-chess-game/" /> <author> <name>pyemma</name> </author> <category term="Distributed System" /> <summary>I have been a fan of online game since my parent bought me a PC when I was in 5th grade. I could still feel the excitement when every Thursday night I rushed home and played DaHuaXiYou 2 with my friends. This is also the direct reason why I decided to major in computer science in college. Today, let’s discuss something related to online game: how to design an online chess game. Functional Requ...</summary> </entry> <entry><title>How Workflow Get Scheduled via Plugins in Flyte</title><link href="https://pyemma.github.io/Flyte-How-Workflow-Get-Scheduled/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Workflow Get Scheduled via Plugins in Flyte" /><published>2024-09-12T00:00:00-07:00</published> <updated>2024-10-05T16:53:30-07:00</updated> <id>https://pyemma.github.io/Flyte-How-Workflow-Get-Scheduled/</id> <content src="https://pyemma.github.io/Flyte-How-Workflow-Get-Scheduled/" /> <author> <name>pyemma</name> </author> <category term="Distributed System" /> <summary>Reading open source code has been a recommended approach for software engineers to learn. However, in my past 8 years career, I didn’t do a good job on that. After working in a startup for 1 year, I accidentally foster the habit to read open source code XD. In this post, I would like to share one open source project I have been learning recently, and hope you would enjoy this journey as well. ...</summary> </entry> </feed>
